Crane Theological School Records UA008
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Crane Theological School Records
1855 -- 1987
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Crane Theological School
Tufts College Divinity School
UA008
8.6 Linear Feet 11 boxes
69 Volumes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in three series: Subject files; Theses; Photographs.
Custodial History
All material accessioned prior to 1997 was originally arranged by subject, no attempt was made to recreate original order, although material relating to administering the collection was removed to the documentation files of the collection in the archives.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, newsletters, announcements, bulletins, lectures, exams, curriculum, programs, minutes, photographs, theses, and conference material. Subjects covered include alumni, faculty, mergers, honorary degree recipients, the library, executive committee, and associations including the Meadville Theological School, the American Unitarian Association, the American Association of Theological Schools, the Massachusetts Universalist Convention, the Unitarian-Universalist Association, the Women's Alliance, the Universalist Historical Society, and the Zetagathean Society.
Biographical / Historical
In 1906, the school received a much-needed gift of $100,000 from Albert Crane, A1863, in memory of his father, Thomas Crane, a trustee from 1852 until his death in 1875. The school was subsequently renamed the Crane Theological School.
Lee Sullivan McCollester became dean of the school in 1912 and brought the school through some of its leanest years, before retiring in 1932. During World War I, the school's buildings were taken for use as barracks and training facilities and Dean McCollester held classes for the handful of students enrolled in his living room for the duration of hostilities. By the mid 1920s enrollments were rising again, and in 1925 the school's name was officially changed to Tufts School of Religion - Crane Theological School. This name continued to be used until the 1960s when it was once again known simply as the Crane Theological School.
There was ongoing debate about whether or not the school should be graduate level only or accept students straight out of secondary school to study for the ministry. For most of its existence the school was an undergraduate professional school, though in later years it succeeded in attracting a growing proportion of students at the graduate level. The school's leadership was concerned that requiring a B.A. for admission would deter worthy candidates from entering the school, while others at the university felt that adequate preparation for a ministerial career required the breadth of a B.A. as well as the specialized training of the B.D. For many years the school offered a combined B.A./S.T.B. (Bachelor of Sacred Theology) degree which was in effect a combined undergraduate and graduate degree. In 1954 the school became strictly a graduate school.
Enrollment at the school reached an all-time high in 1937-38 with sixty students, and in 1941 the school hosted the annual Universalist Convention. Denominational representation in the student body had grown to encompass seven different faiths other than Universalism. While enrollment remained strong in the ensuing years, at roughly forty students, the school struggled to retain full-time faculty, with the majority of positions being filled by part-time faculty shared with the Faculty of Liberal Arts.
In the 1950s and 1960s, discussions were ongoing within the denomination to merge the Crane School with the divinity school at St. Lawrence University, another Universalist school. Tufts was skeptical of the proposal because of the increased role that the denomination would play in the merged institution. An agreement could not be reached, however, and the plan was abandoned.
The decision to close the school was reached by the trustees in June of 1967, to take place the following year. A number of factors contributed to the decision, though the trustees cited the school's failure to maintain its status in religious education. The continual deficit operations of the school undoubtedly also played a part at a time when the university as a whole was facing financial difficulties and the need for retrenchment.
Over the course of its ninety-nine year history, the Crane Theological School granted a total of 485 degrees.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work; Curriculum and Instruction
- Subject files, 1855 -- 1987; 1855 -- 1973; UA008.001; 4.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of subject files containing correspondence, clippings, and reports.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Alumni Association and School News, 1896 -- 1986; UA008.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Dining Room (Paige Hall), 1955 -- 1960; UA008.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Discussion Group, 1962; UA008.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Room (Paige Hall), 1938 -- 1943; UA008.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Theological Schools, 1952 -- 1964; UA008.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - American Unitarian Association, 1935 -- 1956; UA008.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Announcements, Bulletins, 1874 -- 1968; UA008.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Art Objects and Memorabilia, 1942 -- 1965; UA008.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Prizes, 1948 -- 1968; UA008.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Budget and Finances, 1951 -- 1966; UA008.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Door (publication), 1943 -- 1951; UA008.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Chapel services programs, 1961 -- 1966; UA008.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Services programs, 1946 -- 1966; UA008.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1855 -- 1967; UA008.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1869 -- 1923; UA008.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1924 -- 1934; UA008.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1935 -- 1949; UA008.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1951 -- 1963; UA008.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1964 -- 1971; UA008.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Chapel Speakers Fund, 1961 -- 1964; UA008.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Church Funds and Contribution, 1967; UA008.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Continuing Education for Ministers, 1954 -- 1967; UA008.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Convocation, 1955; UA008.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Crane Fellowships, 1965 -- 1967; UA008.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Crane Program, 1968; UA008.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Crane Review, Board Minutes, 1958 -- 1960; UA008.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Crane Review, Copyright Correspondence, 1958 -- 1980; UA008.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Crane Review Correspondence, 1959 -- 1964; UA008.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Crane Review Correspondence, 1965 -- 1966; UA008.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Crane Review Correspondence, 1967 -- 1972; UA008.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum, 1935 -- 1964; UA008.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Dean's Fund: Contribution and Loans, 1947 -- 1967; UA008.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Displaced Persons Project, 1948 -- 1949; UA008.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Divinity School Addresses, 1874; UA008.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Divinity School Anniversary Programs, 1871 -- 1881; UA008.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Examinations, 1907 -- 1966; UA008.001.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee, 1955 -- 1961; UA008.001.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee, 1962 -- 1967; UA008.001.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Faculty, 1951 -- 1966; UA008.001.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Field Education Program, 1965 -- 1966; UA008.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Gifts and Bequests, 1904 -- 1967; UA008.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree Recommendations, 1946 -- 1962; UA008.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Lee S. McCollester Professorship, 1935 -- 1952; UA008.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Library, 1955 -- 1960; UA008.001.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Massachusetts Universalist Convention, 1951 -- 1962; UA008.001.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Meadville Theological School, 1960; UA008.001.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Merger Proposals, 1955 -- 1962; UA008.001.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - Merger Proposals, 1963 -- 1964; UA008.001.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Merger Proposals, St. Lawrence, 1951 -- 1952; UA008.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - Merger Proposals, St. Lawrence, 1961 -- 1962; UA008.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
  - Merger Proposals, St. Lawrence, 1963; UA008.001.006.00003 (Box 6)
  - Merger Proposals, St. Lawrence, 1964; UA008.001.006.00004 (Box 6)
  - Ministerial Testing, 1952 -- 1967; UA008.001.006.00005 (Box 6)
  - Ordination and Recognition Ceremonies, 1889 -- 1968; UA008.001.006.00006 (Box 6)
  - John M. Ratcliff Memorial Lecture, 1955 -- 1963; UA008.001.006.00007 (Box 6)
  - Reports, Meeting Minutes, 1882 -- 1975; UA008.001.006.00008 (Box 6)
  - St. Lawrence University (Theological School), 1960 -- 1965; UA008.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
  - Scholarships, Edith M. Tourtello Scholarship Fund, 1955; UA008.001.007.00002 (Box 7)
  - Scholarships, Pre-Theological, 1955 -- 1958; UA008.001.007.00003 (Box 7)
  - Scholarships, 1909 -- 1987; UA008.001.007.00004 (Box 7)
  - Second Century Fund Campaign, 1950 -- 1953; UA008.001.007.00005 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1955; UA008.001.007.00006 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1956; UA008.001.007.00007 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1957; UA008.001.007.00008 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1958; UA008.001.007.00009 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1959; UA008.001.007.00010 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1961; UA008.001.007.00011 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1963 -- 1964; UA008.001.007.00012 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1967; UA008.001.007.00013 (Box 7)
  - Senexet Conferences, 1968; UA008.001.007.00014 (Box 7)
  - Short History of the Tufts College School of Religion, 1968; UA008.001.007.00015 (Box 7)
  - Skinner Fellowship, 1949 -- 1967; UA008.001.008.00001 (Box 8)
  - Special Services, 1933 -- 1968; UA008.001.008.00002 (Box 8)
  - Starr King School, 1964 -- 1965; UA008.001.008.00003 (Box 8)
  - Summer programs, 1947 -- 1961; UA008.001.008.00004 (Box 8)
  - Tufts Alumni Council, 1956 -- 1961; UA008.001.008.00005 (Box 8)
  - Unitarian--Universalist Association Commission on Education, Liberal Religion, 1960; UA008.001.008.00006 (Box 8)
  - Unitarian--Universalist Association Commission on Education, Liberal Religion, 1961; UA008.001.008.00007 (Box 8)
  - Unitarian--Universalist Association Commission on Education, Liberal Religion, 1962; UA008.001.008.00008 (Box 8)
  - Unitarian--Universalist Association Commission on Education, Liberal Religion, 1963; UA008.001.008.00009 (Box 8)
  - Universalist Fellowship Awards, 1948 -- 1952; UA008.001.009.00001 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - Universalist Ministers' Convocation, 1951 -- 1952; UA008.001.009.00002 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - Women's Alliance, 1959 -- 1961; UA008.001.009.00003 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - Universalist Church of America, 1951 -- 1966; UA008.001.009.00004 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - Universalist Historical Society, 1952 -- 1973; UA008.001.009.00005 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - Zetagathean Society, 1883 -- 1889; UA008.001.009.00006 (Box UA008 Shared 1)
- Theses, 1939 -- 1961; UA008.002; 69 Volumes
  This series consists of theses submitted by students of the Crane Theological School in completion of degree requirements.
  This series is arranged chronologically, then alphabetically.
  - The History of the Follen Church, 1939; UA008.002.011.00001; Brayton, Douglas Percy (Box Volume 11)
    Crane Theological School; School of Religion
  - A Study of Ruralities, 1940; UA008.002.012.00001; Wood, John E. (Box Volume 12)
  - Pastoral Psychology, Working Through Clinics, 1940; UA008.002.013.00001; Brown, Ernest A., Jr. (Box Volume 13)
  - The Management of the Church, The Practical Side, 1940; UA008.002.014.00001; Childers, Oliver W. H. (Box Volume 14)
  - The Disposal of the Dead as a Christian Rite, 1940; UA008.002.015.00001; Gardner, William E. (Box Volume 15)
  - The Church and Juvenile Deliquency, 1940; UA008.002.016.00001; McGinness, Mason F. (Box Volume 16)
  - "The Holy Family" in "Christian Art", 1940; UA008.002.017.00001; McKennay, O. Herbert, Jr. (Box Volume 17)
  - Hymnody in the History of the Christian Church, 1940; UA008.002.018.00001; Stella, Guy T. (Box Volume 18)
  - A Study of the School of Religion Alumni, 1941; UA008.002.019.00001; Domas, Isaiah Jonathan (Box Volume 19)
  - An Analysis of Worship to Determine What Improvements May More Clearly Express the Modern Quest for Religious Experience., 1941; UA008.002.020.00001; Marshall, George N. (Box Volume 20)
  - "Approaches to the Pastoral Problem", 1942; UA008.002.021.00001; Giles, Philip Randall (Box Volume 21)
  - The Apocalyptic Movement, 1942; UA008.002.022.00001; Perry, Albert Q. (Box Volume 22)
    School of Religion; Crane Theological School
  - A Preliminary Study of Happiness as it Appears in the Sermons of Cotton Mathers, 1942; UA008.002.023.00001; Robinson, Morris Reed (Box Volume 23)
  - The Radical Empiricism of James---Its Appreciation and Criticism, 1943; UA008.002.024.00001; Cobb, Maurice W. (Box Volume 24)
  - Hosea Ballou, 1943; UA008.002.025.00001; Klotzle, Dana E. (Box Volume 25)
  - Is Birth Control Immoral?, 1942; UA008.002.009.00007; Smith, Howard F., Jr. (Box UA008 Shared 1)
  - A Liberal Policy for Protestant Unity, 1943; UA008.002.027.00001; Bodge, J. Everett (Box Volume 27)
  - A Collection of Historical Material Relating to the History of Unitarianism in Maine, 1944; UA008.002.028.00001; Findly, John K. (Box Volume 28)
  - The Rural Church and the Rural Community and their Place in Society, 1944; UA008.002.029.00001; Hosmer, Robert G. (Box Volume 29)
  - An Order of Church for Free Church Worship, 1944; UA008.002.030.00001; Royce, Burchard A., Jr. (Box Volume 30)
  - What is Anti-Seminism, 1944; UA008.002.031.00001; Adams, Eugene H. (Box Volume 31)
  - Christian Symbolism, 1945; UA008.002.032.00001; Wyatt, Kenneth B. (Box Volume 32)
  - A Functional Theology for Liberal Religion, 1945; UA008.002.033.00001; Ziegler, Albert Frederick (Box Volume 33)
  - The Present Status of Liberal Religious Thought in regard to immortality, 1945; UA008.002.034.00001; McKeeman, Gordon B. (Box Volume 34)
  - Philosophy and Religion, 1944; UA008.002.035.00001; Lapoint, George M. (Box Volume 35)
  - The Unitarian Service Committee, 1945; UA008.002.036.00001; D'Orlando, Albert (Box Volume 36)
  - A History of Universalism in Portsmouth, New Hampshire, 1945; UA008.002.037.00001; Thorsell, Ernest A. (Box Volume 37)
  - A Century of Attempted Rapprochment Between the Universalist Church of America and the American Unitarian Association, 1945; UA008.002.038.00001; Vickery, Charles N. (Box Volume 38)
  - The Reign of King Soloman in the Light of Recent Archaeological Investigation, 1945; UA008.002.039.00001; Fay, Leon Converse (Box Volume 39)
  - The Pauline Eschatology, 1945; UA008.002.040.00001; Nargesian, Haig J. (Box Volume 40)
  - "Through the Years", 1945; UA008.002.041.00001; Robertson, John Prescott (Box Volume 41)
  - The Eastern Orthodox-Catholic Church and The Anglican Church: Their Union, 1945; UA008.002.042.00001; de Vie, D. C. (Box Volume 42)
  - Reorganizing the Rural Church, 1945; UA008.002.043.00001; Hirons, Frank T. (Box Volume 43)
  - A Common Faith: Elements in the Philosophy of Religion of John Dewey, 1946; UA008.002.044.00001; Hutchinson, James M. (Box Volume 44)
  - Paul's Idea of God, 1946; UA008.002.045.00001; McKinney, Earle T. (Box Volume 45)
  - History of Communion and Its Place in the Liberal Church, 1946; UA008.002.046.00001; Munson, Keith C. (Box Volume 46)
  - Visual Education in the Church, 1946; UA008.002.047.00001; Niles, George L. (Box Volume 47)
  - The Social Application of Universalism, 1947; UA008.002.048.00001; Brown, J. Alden (Box Volume 48)
  - The History of the Union Congregational Church of Magnolia from 1887 to 1944, 1947; UA008.002.049.00001; Browne, William J. (Box Volume 49)
  - The Vacation Church School, 1947; UA008.002.050.00001; Christensen, John P. (Box Volume 50)
  - The Religious Foundation of Zionism, 1947; UA008.002.051.00001; Cole, Davd H. (Box Volume 51)
  - Thomas Stearns Eliot -- A Search for Faith, 1947; UA008.002.052.00001; Markuson, Aaron (Box Volume 52)
  - The Ethical Philosophy of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1947; UA008.002.053.00001; Nelson, L. Edward (Box Volume 53)
  - Universalist Interpretations, Selected Philosohical and Theological Contributors of Universalists, 1770-1947, UA008.002.054.00001; Pennington, George J. W. (Box Volume 54)
  - A Survey of the Homiletics Departments of Four Greater Boston Theological Schools, 1947; UA008.002.055.00001; Tripp, Arthur H. (Box Volume 55)
  - Religious Humanism, 1946; UA008.002.056.00001; Henriksen, Alfred J. N. (Box Volume 56)
  - A Study of the Curriculum in Universalist Churches in Massachusetts, 1948; UA008.002.057.00001; MacPherson, Robert H. (Box Volume 57)
  - The Problem of Racial Integration and the Liberal Church, 1949; UA008.002.058.00001; Deas, Henri M. (Box Volume 58)
  - A Functional Philosophy of Worship for the Liberal Church, 1949; UA008.002.059.00001; Hopkins, Raymond C. (Box Volume 59)
  - Humanist Worship, 1947; UA008.002.060.00001; Westwood, Arnold Farrow (Box Volume 60)
  - Improving the Time Factor in Religious Education, 1950; UA008.002.061.00001; Hilton, Hope (Box Volume 61)
  - Concepts of Wisdom in the Apocrypha and the Pseudepigrapha, 1950; UA008.002.062.00001; Miller, Robert L. H. (Box Volume 62)
  - Burying The Dead, 1951; UA008.002.063.00001; Crook, Gordon A. (Box Volume 63)
  - Unitarianism in Czechoslovakia, 1950; UA008.002.064.00001; Kafka, Hvezdon (Box Volume 64)
  - The Salvation Army - Its Development and Service, 1951; UA008.002.065.00001; Tate, Harmon R. (Box Volume 65)
  - Adult Religious Education in the Church, 1951; UA008.002.066.00001; Van de Workeen, Melvin C. (Box Volume 66)
  - The Church and the Indians of South Dakota: Conditions, Past and Present, 1952; UA008.002.067.00001; Brown, Arnold Marshall (Box Volume 67)
  - Trends in the Universalist Churches in the First Half of the Twentieth Century, 1952; UA008.002.068.00001; MacPherson, David Hicks (Box Volume 68)
  - Social Implications of New England Transcendentalism, 1952; UA008.002.069.00001; Anderson, Francis C., Jr. (Box Volume 69)
  - Humanism, 1952; UA008.002.070.00001; Burlingame, Edwin Clark (Box Volume 70)
  - The Christian Source of Anti-Seminism (Especially the New Testament, and The Fathers), 1952; UA008.002.071.00001; Clark, Edmund Palmer (Box Volume 71)
  - Extending the Field of Unitarianism, 1952; UA008.002.072.00001; Wahlstrom, Frank A. (Box Volume 72)
  - The Rise of Unitarianism in America, 1953; UA008.002.073.00001; Chapple, John Hunt (Box Volume 73)
  - Abner Kneeland: Religious Pioneer, 1953; UA008.002.074.00001; Sherman, Harry M. (Box Volume 74)
  - The Anthem and the American Liberal College, 1953; UA008.002.075.00001; Hanhisalo, J. Henry (Box Volume 75)
  - Cotton Mather and the Possessed, 1954; UA008.002.076.00001; Cassara, Ernest (Box Volume 76)
  - The Problem of the Trinity, 1954; UA008.002.077.00001; Mofford, David Gordon (Box Volume 77)
  - The Kingdom Explained by the Parables, 1955; UA008.002.078.00001; Holman, John L., Jr. (Box Volume 78)
  - Clarence R. Skinner: image of a movement, 1961; UA008.002.079.00001; Gaines, Charles A. (Box Volume 79)
    Crane Theological School
- Photographs, 1887 -- 1965; UA008.003; 1.7 Linear Feet
  This series consists of photographs from the Crane Theological School and its predecessor, the School of Religion.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Photos, 1887 -- 1897; UA008.003.010.00001 (Box 10)
  - Photos, 1901 -- 1907; UA008.003.010.00002 (Box 10)
  - Photos, 1930 -- 1939; UA008.003.010.00003 (Box 10)
  - Photos, 1940 -- 1949; UA008.003.010.00004 (Box 10)
  - Photos, 1940 -- 1959; UA008.003.010.00005 (Box 10)
  - Photos, 1960 -- 1965; UA008.003.010.00006 (Box 10)
  - Senior Class Photo, 1897; UA008.003.010.00007 (Box Shared 4)
    This photograph was found uncatalogued in the stacks in summer 2007. Note its different location; it is housed in a separate box with other oversize materials. Date is approximate.